<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alex J. Hope on Alex J. Hope</title>
    <link>https://ehhope.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Alex J. Hope on Alex J. Hope</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>NBA Shot Classifier</title>
      <link>https://ehhope.github.io/project/nba-shot-decision-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 01:26:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ehhope.github.io/project/nba-shot-decision-tree/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;decision-tree-analysis-of-makes-misses-in-the-nba&#34;&gt;Decision Tree Analysis of Makes &amp;amp; Misses in the NBA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;a-case-study-lebron-james&#34;&gt;A case study: Lebron James&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ehhope/LBJ-for-Tree&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; focuses on the 2014-2015 NBA season with a dataset containing characteristics of every shot (shot distance, defender, shot clock, etc.) taken by every player in the NBA. The approach used a decision tree classifier to predict whether a shot was made or missed based on shot features for each shot taken by the player. Lebron James season with the Cleveland Cavaliers was used as a case example, however, the script is flexible enough to wrangle, visualize with several plots, analyze and report data for any player if specified as an argument when using &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our decision tree classifier predicted Lebron James at a marginal ~65% when hyperparameters were optimized, however, other players we were able to score upwards of 85%. The reason for the model&amp;rsquo;s poor accuracy with Lebron James, Steph Curry, and other top shooters is that the features don&amp;rsquo;t segregate makes/misses as cleanly as players who are reliably poor shooters based on changes in particular features such as shot distance. An NBA center will struggle to shoot long range shots, therefore when shot distance increases, our classifier is quite accurate in predicting the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is also reproducible through &lt;code&gt;docker&lt;/code&gt;. Inside the repository linked below, you will find a dockerfile with instructions for running all of the scripts with their respective dependencies (R and python libraries). If you don&amp;rsquo;t have all of the dependencies installed locally that&amp;rsquo;s ok, just use the dockerfile written to run the scripts in the container provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For easily reproducing and generating data regarding NBA players, this project uses &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; to run multiple scripts in terminal as well. If interested, you can find the repository on my github account &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ehhope/LBJ-for-Tree&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; with instructions in the README file for using these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BRIEF Intervention</title>
      <link>https://ehhope.github.io/project/brief-intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 03:15:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ehhope.github.io/project/brief-intervention/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Neurophysiology of Motor Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://ehhope.github.io/publication/neurophysiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 18:51:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ehhope.github.io/publication/neurophysiology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The strong relationship between motor and cognitive development suggests that the limited motor experience of children with physical disabilities can impact their cognitive and perceptual development. The assessment of their cognitive skills is also compromised due to limited verbal communication and motor gestures. Robots have been used to give children with disabilities an opportunity to independently manipulate objects and to reveal their cognitive skills when they use the robots. Little is known about the neural correlates that subtend robotic augmentative manipulation and the ways in which using a robot to manipulate objects may change the task&amp;rsquo;s cognitive and perceptual demands. Several technical considerations pose a challenge to such studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: This paper presents a methodology for the technical implementation of neurophysiological exploration of robot-augmented manipulation and presents an evaluation of the technical feasibility of performing a comparison between augmented manipulation and direct manipulation as response modalities in a cognitive task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;METHODS: A costume made interface was designed that would allow the interfacing of the EGI NetStation Electroencephalographic (EEG) signal acquisition system, the E-Prime stimulus presentation system, and a 3-Dimensional task performed with either a robot or through typical direct manipulation. The technical feasibility and the stability of the designed technical implementation was tested with 10 adult participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RESULTS: Initial analysis revealed specific robot control interface related artifacts. Further testing confirmed the source of artifact. Independent Component Analysis (ICA) was successfully used to separate this artifact component. Advantages, disadvantages, and results obtained from this method for technical implementation are presented. Implications for the study of neural correlates of augmentative manipulation are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
